<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book status="final" security="public"><title>Performance Co-Pilot&#x2122; Tutorials and Case Studies</title>
<bookinfo><edition>3</edition>

<othercredit>
<contrib>Maintained by</contrib>
<affiliation>
<orgname>The Performance Co-Pilot Development Team</orgname>
<address>
<email>pcp@oss.sgi.com</email>
<otheraddr>
<ulink url="http://pcp.io"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/pcp.svg"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
</otheraddr>
</address>
</affiliation>
</othercredit>

<copyright>
<year>2012</year>
<year>2014</year>
<holder>Red Hat, Inc.</holder>
</copyright>

<copyright>
<year>2007</year>
<year>2013</year>
<holder>Aconex.</holder>
</copyright>

<copyright>
<year>2000</year>
<year>2013</year>
<holder>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</holder>
</copyright>

<legalnotice>
<title>LICENSE</title>
<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute, and/or modify this document under
the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike, Version 3.0 or any
later version published by the Creative Commons Corp.
A copy of the license is available at
<ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/us/"/></para>
</legalnotice>

<legalnotice>
<title>TRADEMARKS AND ATTRIBUTIONS</title>
<para>Red Hat and the Shadowman logo are trademarks of Red Hat, Inc.,
registered in the United States and other countries.</para>
<para>Silicon Graphics, SGI and the SGI logo are registered trademarks
and Performance Co-Pilot is a trademark of Silicon Graphics, Inc.</para>
<para>Cisco is a registered trademark of Cisco Systems, Inc.
Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds, used with permission.
UNIX is a registered trademark of The Open Group.</para>
</legalnotice>

<revhistory>
<revision><revnumber>001</revnumber><date>August 2013</date><revremark>Initial collation.</revremark></revision>
</revhistory>

</bookinfo>
<toc/>


<preface id="id5178752">

<title>About This Book</title>
<para>This book is a collection of tutorials, case studies, and short stories about
various aspects of the Performance Co-Pilot (PCP) performance analysis toolkit.
Topics range from basic installation through to detailed analysis techniques,
with everything in-between, that even seasoned PCP users can expect to learn from.
</para>
<para>Much like PCP is an open source, cross-platform software package - where
customizations are actively encouraged - so too is this book. If you have
interesting experiences to share, please consider contibuting - the XML source
to this book is available, along with the PCP source code.</para>
<para>&#x201C;About This Book&#x201D; includes short descriptions of the chapters
in this book, directs you to additional sources of information, and explains
typographical conventions.</para>
<section id="id5178771">

<title>What This Book Contains</title>
<para>This book contains the following chapters:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="LE21795-PARENT"/>, contains introductory topics around installation of PCP.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="LE98072-PARENT"/>, contains a series of hands-on tutorials covering use of specific PCP monitor tools, secure collector setup.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><xref linkend="LE25915-PARENT"/>, provides a set of case studies of use of PCP to address problems, or understand certain system behaviours using PCP.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>It provides a series of real-world examples of using various PCP tools,
and lessons learned from deploying the toolkit in production environments.
It serves to provide reinforcement of the general concepts discussed in the
other books described in the <xref linkend="id5178933"/>, with additional case
studies and more detailed discussion of individual tools.</para>
</section>
<section id="id5178891">

<title>Audience for This Book</title>
<para>This book has something for everyone - early topics will aid those getting
started with PCP, while later sections cover in-depth material, sometimes requiring
detailed understanding of operating system internals.</para>
<para>Some familiarity with the basic concepts behind PCP is assumed.</para>
</section>
<section id="id5178933">

<title>Related Resources</title>
<para>The <citetitle>Performance Co-Pilot User's and Administrator's Guide</citetitle>
is intended for system administrators and performance analysts who are directly
using and administering PCP installations.</para>
<para>The <citetitle>Performance Co-Pilot Programmer's Guide</citetitle>
is intended for developers who want to use the PCP framework and services for
exporting additional collections of performance metrics, or for delivering
new or customized applications to enhance performance management.
</para>
<para>Additional resources include man pages and the project web site.</para>
</section>
<section id="id5178968">

<title>Man Pages</title>
<para>The operating system man pages provide concise reference information on the use of commands, subroutines, and system resources. There is usually a man page for each PCP command or subroutine. To see a list of all the PCP man pages, start from the following command:</para>
<literallayout class="monospaced"><userinput>man PCPIntro</userinput></literallayout>
<para>Each man page usually has a &quot;SEE ALSO&quot; section, linking to other, related entries.</para>
<para>To see a particular man page, supply its name to the <literal>man</literal> command, for example:</para>
<literallayout class="monospaced"><userinput>man pcp</userinput></literallayout>
<para>The man pages are arranged in different sections separating commands, programming interfaces, and so on.
For a complete list of manual sections on a platform enter the command:</para>
<literallayout class="monospaced"><userinput>man man</userinput></literallayout>
<para>When referring to man pages, this guide follows a standard convention: the section number in parentheses follows the item. For example, <command>pminfo(1)</command> refers to the man page in section 1 for the <command>pminfo</command> command.</para>
</section>
<section id="id5179157">

<title>Web Site</title>
<para>The following web site is accessible to everyone:</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><emphasis role="bold">URL</emphasis></term><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><ulink url="http://pcp.io">http://pcp.io</ulink></term>
<listitem><para>PCP is open source software released under
the GNU General Public License (GPL) and GNU Lesser General Public License (LGPL)</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section id="id5179276">

<title>Conventions</title>
<para>The following conventions are used throughout this document:<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><emphasis role="bold">Convention</emphasis></term><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Meaning</emphasis></para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><literal>${PCP_VARIABLE}</literal></term>
<listitem><para>A brace-enclosed all-capital-letters syntax indicates a variable
that has been sourced from the global <filename>/etc/pcp.conf</filename> file.
These special variables indicate parameters that affect all PCP commands,
and are likely to be different between platforms.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><literal>command</literal></term>
<listitem><para>This fixed-space font denotes literal items such as commands,
files, routines, path names, signals, messages, and programming language
structures. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><replaceable>variable</replaceable></term>
<listitem><para>Italic typeface denotes variable entries and words or concepts being
defined.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><userinput>user input</userinput></term>
<listitem><para>This bold, fixed-space font denotes literal  items that the user enters in interactive  sessions.  (Output is shown in nonbold,  fixed-space font.)</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>[ ]</term>
<listitem><para>Brackets enclose optional portions of a  command or directive line.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>...</term>
<listitem><para>Ellipses indicate that a preceding element can be repeated.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>ALL CAPS</term>
<listitem><para>All capital letters denote environment variables, operator names, directives, defined constants, and macros in C programs.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>()</term>
<listitem><para>Parentheses that follow function names surround function arguments or are empty if the function has no arguments; parentheses that follow commands surround man page section numbers.</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist></para>

</section>
<section id="z825546061melby">

<title>Reader Comments</title>
<para>If you have comments about the technical accuracy, content, or organization of this document, contact the PCP maintainers using either the email address or the web site listed earlier.</para>
<para>We value your comments and will respond to them promptly.</para>
</section>
</preface>


<chapter id="LE21795-PARENT">

<title>Supported Platforms Installation</title>
<para>Binary packages for Linux (deb and rpm formats), Mac OS X, Solaris and Windows are
made available by the PCP development team.</para>
<para>These are all freely available from the download section of the PCP project web site.</para>

<section id="id5177140">

<title>Linux Installation</title>
<para><indexterm id="IG313401778"><primary>Linux</primary></indexterm>Pre-packaged binaries are available for the Linux platform ... XXX</para>
</section>
<section id="id5177343">

<title>Mac OS X Installation</title>
<para><indexterm id="IG313401779"><primary>Mac OS X</primary></indexterm>After downloading the <literal>dmg</literal> file for your platform, double-click on the PCP <literal>dmg</literal> icon in the Finder application, and follow the installation instructions presented by the Installer.</para>
<para>Mac OS X versions 10.5 and onward are generally available, although older versions can be built from source.</para>
</section>
<section id="id5177529">

<title>Solaris Installation</title>
<para><indexterm id="IG313401780"><primary>Solaris</primary></indexterm>Download and unzip the latest binary package from the PCP project web site.</para>
<para>To install the package for the first time, issue the following commands:</para>
<programlisting><userinput>pkgadd -d pcp-${PCP_VERSION}</userinput>
  Say 'y' to all of the questions.
<userinput>svcadm enable pmcd</userinput></programlisting>
<para>To upgrade an existing installation, issue the following commands:</para>
<programlisting><userinput>pkgadd -d pcp-${PCP_VERSION}</userinput>
<userinput>pkgadd -d pcp-${PCP_VERSION}</userinput>
<userinput>svcadm enable pmcd</userinput></programlisting>
</section>
<section id="id5177616">

<title>Windows Installation</title>
<para><indexterm id="IG313401781"><primary>Windows</primary></indexterm> After downloading the PCP Glider <literal>msi</literal> file, right-click on the command prompt icon, select <literal>Run As Administrator</literal>, and enter:</para>
<programlisting><userinput>msiexec /i pcp-glider-${PCP_VERSION}.msi</userinput>
<userinput>cd C:\Glider\scripts</userinput>
<userinput>postinst.bat</userinput></programlisting>
<para>The command line utilities can now be accessed from a Windows shell or the provided (POSIX) shell. The graphical tools can be accessed via the Windows <literal>Start</literal> menu.</para>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter id="LE98072-PARENT">

<title>Tutorials</title>
<para>From a high-level PCP can be considered to contain two classes of software utility:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>PCP Collectors. These are the parts of PCP that collect and extract performance data from various domains, such as the kernel or a database.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>PCP Monitors.  These are the parts of PCP that display data collected from hosts (or archives) that have the PCP Collector installed.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>The tutorials of this section focus on various monitoring tools initially, and then finish up with some extensions to collector systems not covered in the <citetitle>Performance Co-Pilot User's and Administrator's Guide</citetitle>.</para>

<section id="id5187772">
<title>Using PCP Charts</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5188149">
<title>Logging Basics</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5188221">
<title>Automated Reasoning</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter id="LE25915-PARENT">
<title>Case Studies</title>

<section id="id5187771">
<title>Understanding System-Level Processor Performance</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5187773">
<title>Understanding Measures of Disk Performance</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5187774">
<title>An Operating System Upgrade Evaluation</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5187775">
<title>Comparing Storage System Performance</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>

<section id="id5187776">
<title>Central Logging: Instrumenting Distributed Event Logs</title>
<para>...</para>
</section>


</chapter>


<index id="sgi-index">

<indexentry>
   <primaryie>Linux <link linkend="IG313401778">Supported Platforms Installation</link></primaryie>
</indexentry>

<indexentry>
   <primaryie>Max OS X <link linkend="IG313401779">Supported Platform Installations</link></primaryie>
</indexentry>

<indexentry>
   <primaryie>Solaris <link linkend="IG313401780">Supported Platform Installations</link></primaryie>
</indexentry>

<indexentry>
   <primaryie>Windows <link linkend="IG313401781">Supported Platforms Installation</link></primaryie>
</indexentry>

</index>

</book>
